ucas C.Wheeler, Ph

■ lucas.wheeler@colorado.edu | 🌴 https://lcwheeler.github.io/ | 🖸 lcwheeler | 💆 @LCWheeler9000

Research Interests

My research interests are focused on understanding the interactions between different biological scales. For example, how are genetic changes manifested at the biochemical and cellular levels and in turn at the level of organismal phenotypes and ecological effects? I aim to develop a research program that addresses these fundamental questions using plant secondary metabolism as a model system. I strive to use experiments, field studies, and computational modeling to develop a framework for unifying biological scales and understanding emergent properties of biological systems.

Research Experience

University of Colorado-Boulder

Jan 2018 – present

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCH

Boulder, CO

- · I am using transcriptomics, biochemistry, functional genetics, and bioinformatics to study the evolution of floral coloration in the Petunieae sub-family of Solanaceae.
- I have developed a computational approach for modeling the evolution of metabolic pathways and used it to simulate the evolution of the anthocyanin pigmentation pathway.

University of Oregon Sep 2012 - Dec 2017

GRADUATE RESEARCH

Eugene, OR

- · Designed an experiment that coupled ancestral sequence reconstruction with high-throughput binding experiments to study the evolution of target binding specificity in the S100 protein family.
- Studied the evolution of metal binding affinity and specificity in the S100 protein family using calorimetry and phylogenetics.

Montana State University

Sep 2009 - June 2012

UNDERGRADUATE RESEARCH

Bozeman, MT

• Engineered virus-like particles containing various functional peptides including defensins and conotoxins, for biomedical applications.

Publications

Wheeler LC, Stacey SD (2019). Computational modeling of anthocyanin pathway evolution: Biases, hotspots, and trade-offs. Integrative and Comparative Biology.

Hiranmayi Duvvuri, Wheeler LC, Harms MJ (2018). pytc: open source python software for global analyses of isothermal titration calorimetry data. Biochemistry.

Wheeler LC, Anderson JA, Morrison AJ, Wong CE, Harms MJ (2017) Conservation of specificity intwo low-specificity proteins. Biochemistry.

Wheeler LC, Harms MJ (2017). S100A5 binds Ca2+ and Cu2+ independently. BMC Biophysics.

Wheeler LC, Donor MT, Prell JS, Harms MJ (2016). Multiple Evolutionary Origins of Ubiquitous Cu2+ and Zn2+ Binding in the S100 protein Family. PLoS ONE.

Wheeler LC, An-Lim S, Margusee S, Harms MJ (2016). The thermostability and specificity of ancient proteins. Current Opinions in Structural Biology.

Education

University of Oregon

Ph.D. IN BIOCHEMISTRY

Eugene, Oregon

Sep. 2012 - Dec. 2017

· Completed my PhD in the lab of Dr. Michael J. Harms

Montana State University

Bozeman, MT

B.S. IN BIOCHEMISTRY

Sep. 2009 - June 2012

• Graduated with honors from Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry

Teaching Experience _____

2019 -		Pinhead Punk
	Floral Pigmentation Lab, Volunteer Instructor	Science (Telluride,
present		CO)
2018 -		CU Boulder Upward
present	Floral Pigmentation Lab and Lecture, Volunteer Instructor	Bound
2013	Biochemistry Recitation, Instructor	University of Oregon
2013	Biochemistry Laboratory, Teaching assistant	University of Oregon
2012	General Chemistry Laboratory, Teaching assistant	University of Oregon

Honors & Awards _____

INTERNATIONAL

2015	Mechanisms of Protein Evolution III: Best Student Talk, Winner	Denver, CO
2015	Mechanisms of Protein Evolution III: Student Travel Award, Recipient	Denver, CO
2011-2012	Montana INBRE Research Award, Recipient	Bozeman, MT
2011	Geer-Howald-Callis & Swager Summer Research Awards, Recipient	Bozeman, MT

Strengths & Skills_____

Molecular Biology	Gene cloning, RNA/DNA extraction, preparation of NGS libraries, Virus-induced gene silencing
Biochemistry/Biophysics	Protein expression & purification, Isothermal Titration Calorimetry, Circular Dichroism Spectroscopy, HPLC
Botanical Field Work	Plant collections, Preservation of tissues, Reflectance spectroscopy, Photography, Microscopy
Scientific Programming	Python, R, Julia, Snakemake, Jupyter, Git & Github
Bioinformatics Tools	Trinity, Salmon & Kallisto, Sleuth & DEseq2, BBtools, BWA, PhyML, RaxML, & ExaBayes
Languages	English (native), Spanish (intermediate)

Service & Outreach	
Citizens' Climate Lobby	Golden, CO
Volunteer	2018 - present
Quantitative Problem Solving & Research Communication Consortium	Eugene, OR
CO-CHAIR	2016 - 2017
UO SafeRide Program	Eugene, OR
Volunteer	2018 - present
Mad Duck Science Fridays	Eugene, OR
Volunteer	2013 - 2017
Associated Students of MSU	Bozeman, MT
STUDENT SENATOR	2010 - 2011
Undergraduate Chemistry Society	Bozeman, MT
SECRETARY & VICE-PRESIDENT	2009 - 2012
Sacajawea Middle School	Bozeman, MT
Volunteer Mentor	2009-2010

Juniper Elementary School

VOLUNTEER MENTOR FOR STUDENTS WITH SPECIAL NEEDS

Bend, OR

2005 - 2008

Conference Presentations _____

Evolution meeting	Providence, RI
Preferential fixation of structural or regulatory mutations depends on pathway position" Submitted talk	June 2019
Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology	Tampa, FL
Computational modeling of anthocyanin pathway evolution" Submitted talk	Jan. 2019
Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution	Austin, TX
Phage display and deep sequencing to study the evolution of binding specificity" Submitted talk	July 2017
hird International Symposium on Protein Folding and Dynamics	Bangalore, India
Tracing the evolution of peptide binding specificity in the \$100 protein family using phage display and deep equencing" Submitted talk	Nov. 2016
Sibbs Conference on Biological Thermodynamics	Carbondale, IL
Preferential fixation of structural or regulatory mutations depends on pathway position" Submitted talk	Sep. 2016
Mechanisms of Protein Evolution III: Origins	Denver, CO
Tracing the evolutionary fluctuations of peptide binding specificity in the \$100 protein family" Submitted talk	Nov. 2015
Sibbs Conference on Biological Thermodynamics	Carbondale, IL
Tracing the evolutionary fluctuations of peptide binding specificity in the \$100 protein family" Submitted poster	Sep. 2015
Protein Folding Consortium Workshop	Berkeley, CA
Probing the evolutionary history of peptide binding specificity in the \$100 protein family" Submitted talk	May. 2015
Sibbs Conference on Biological Thermodynamics	Carbondale, IL
Evolutionary biophysical studies of peptide specificity in the \$100s" Submitted poster	Sep. 2014
Protein Folding Consortium Workshop	Ann Arbor, MI
EVOLUTIONARY BIOPHYSICAL STUDIES OF PROTEIN FUNCTION IN THE \$100 FAMILY"	May. 2014

• Submitted poster